Today's דף Daf is כ"ח Chaf-Chet (28), but we'll first
start with finishing up the yesterday's דף Daf slide.
Yesterday's דף, Daf, we were on the beginning of כ"ז עמוד
ב', Chaf-Zayin Amud-Beis, and the question here is that we have a
contradiction of ברייתות. Braitot. One says the sprinkling of blood of
the various things that are sprinkled toward the היכל, Heichal, if it's
not precise, it's כשר, Kasher, and the other said no, normally it's
כשר Kasher but by the פרה אדומה Parah Adumah it's פסול. Passul.
So the question is, what is this debate about? And this is
in the larger context of things that are מעכב, Me'akev, prevent things
from being valid, although normally we're talking about different component parts that
prevent things from being valid. Okay, so pick up with the גמרא
Gemara says like this: So it quoted a question about when a
כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, when a non-כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, and it's
not יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, enters it into the קדש הקדשים, Kodesh
Hakodashim, the Torah says that he is ולא ימות, v'lo yamut, חייב
מיתה. chayav mita. And the question is, is the חיוב מיתה chiyuv
mita only for when he enters directly in front of the ארון,
Aron, or anywhere in the קדש הקדשים? Kodesh Hakodashim? So we pick
up with that and the גמרא Gemara says like this:
Where are we?
במאי קמיפלגי? B'mai kamifligi? בהאי קרא. Behai Kra. Okay, in the following
verse. So it starts with the word, did we read that far
yesterday?
No, maybe not.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this, let's take אמר רב
חסדא. Amar Rav Chisda. אמר רב חסדא, Amar Rav Chisda, one, two,
three, four, five, six, seven lines from the top, end of the
line. אמר רב חסדא, Amar Rav Chisda, לא קשיא. lo kashya. Line
starts with the word ל"ק Lamed Kof with a tship-tshik. לא קשיא,
lo kashya, it's not difficult. הא רבי יהודה הא רבנן. Ha Rabbi
Yehuda Ha Rabbanan. It's a debate of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and
the רבנן Rabbanan whether the idea of towards is precise or not.
What does this mean? דתניא, Detanya, we taught in a ברייתא. Braita.
מחוסרי כפרה שנכנסו לעזרה בשוגג. Mechusrei Kaparah shenichnesu la'azarah bishogeg. Somebody who
lacks atonement, which really means that their טהרה tahara process has not
completed because they still have to bring a
קרבן. Korban. So it is the lowest level of
טהרה tahara because of טומאה, tumah, because everything is done except for
the final bringing of the קרבן. Korban. So that is מחוסרי כפרה.
Mechusrei Kapara. Now what did they do? מחוסרי כפרה שנכנסו לעזרה בשוגג.
Mechusrei Kapara shenichnesu la'azarah bishogeg. They entered into the עזרה, Azarah, the
Temple courtyard, the Temple grounds proper where there is the מזבח, Mizbeach,
unintentionally. חייב חטאת, Chayav Chatat, they bring a sin offering because that's
the classic example of a טמא tamei that enters into the בית
המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, although it's only a residual טומאה. tumah. במזיד, B'meizid,
if they do it willfully, ענוש כרת, Anosh Kares, punishable by כרת.
Kares. ואין צריך לומר, V'ein tzarich lomar, it goes without saying people
that have more than just a residual טומאה. tumah. טבול יום, Tvu-el
Yom, somebody who had to the מקווה Mikveh that day but it
hadn't been nightfall, that's also residual but not as residual as the
person that only needs to bring the קרבן. Korban. ושאר כל הטמאים,
V'shaar kol hatmei'in, and certainly people of a more טמא, tamei, it's
more טמא, tamei, and certainly people that are fully טמא tamei that
haven't even gone to the מקווה, Mikveh, if they enter into the
Temple courtyard, what? They get כרת, Kares, right? They get כרת Kares
and if it's בשוגג bishogeg they bring a חטאת. chatat. Now, period.
Here's the part that's relevant for us. הטהורים שנכנסו לפנים ממחיצתן, Hat'horim
shenichnesu lifnim mimchitzatan, even people that are pure that go beyond their
boundaries, beyond where they're allowed to go. להיכל כולו בארבעים. Leheichal kulo
b'arba'im. So if they go into anywhere in the היכל, Heichal, which
is you know the אוהל מועד Ohel Moed counterpart, it's where you
had the שולחן Shulchan and the gold מזבח, Mizbeach, it was the
part that was roofed, right? Was the inner sanctum but not the
קדש הקדשים. Kodesh Hakodashim. So then it is punishable by lashes because
it says ולא יבא בכל עת, V'Lo Yavo Bechol Et, you shall
not come, which is a negative prohibition, even if you're טהור tahor
and even if you are a כהן, Kohen, if you do not
have a right to be there. And certainly if you are a
non-כהן. Kohen. The issue about a כהן Kohen going in without a
purpose is
called a ביאה ריקנית, bi'ah reikanit, an entering in for no purpose.
So let's bracket that, but certainly if you're not a כהן, Kohen,
you get lashes. אל פני הכפורת, El pnei hakaporeth, if you actually
present yourself in front of the ארון, Aron, right in front of...
then במיתה. b'mitah. Did I skip a line?
No, but I did skip a word. מבית לפרוכת, Mibeit laparohet, behind
the curtain, in the קדש הקדשים, Kodesh Hakodashim, אל פני הכפורת, el
pnei hakaporeth, or certainly if you're in front of the ארון, Aron,
במיתה, b'mita, then it's a חיוב מיתה chiyuv mita not by the
court but by God. That's the first position. רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi
Yehuda Omer, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says: כל ההיכל כולו ומבית לפרוכת
בארבעים. Kol haHeichal kulo umibeit laparohet b'arba'im. No, the entire היכל Heichal
and including the קדש הקדשים Kodesh Hakodashim is only lashes, is only
40 lashes. ואל פני הכפורת, V'el pnei hakaporeth, the only thing the
Torah says that is punishable by divine death is directly in front
of the ארון, Aron, במיתה. b'mita. That's מיתה. mita. במאי קמיפלגי? B'mai
kamifligi? What is this debate? בהאי קרא, Behai kra, the following פסוק,
pasuk, where do you put the
comma in the פסוק? pasuk? Okay, here's the פסוק. pasuk. ויאמר ה'
אל משה, Vayomer Hashem el Moshe, so it's coming up one פרשה
parsha away. דבר אל אהרן אחיך, Daber el Aharon achicha, speak to
Aharon your brother, ואל יבא בכל עת אל הקדש, v'al yavo bechol
et el hakodesh, he may not enter into the sanctuary at any
time he wants. So that's a negative prohibition to go in. without
a legitimate purpose into the היכל Heichal *Heichal*, מבית לפרוכת mibeis laparoches
*mibeis laporeches* into behind the פרוכת paroches *paroches*, the קודש קדשים Kodesh
Kodashim *Kodesh Kodashim*, על פני הכפורת al pnei hakaporet. אשר על al
הארון *al penei hakaporeth asher al ha'aron* in the in front of
the כפורת kaporeis *kaporeth*, the plate, the cover that is on the
ארון aron? *aron* ולא ימות *veloy amus* and he shall not die.
So of course situate you have three words אל el הקדש *el
hakodesh*, מבית לפרוכת mibeis laparoches *mibeis laporeches*, על פני הכפורת p'nei hakaporeis,
*al penei hakaporeth*. So certainly you shall not come אל el הקדש
*el hakodesh* is clear. Certainly what's also clear is על פני הכפורת
p'nei hakaporeis ולא ימות *al penei hakaporeth veloy amus*. If you're in
front of the כפורת kaporeis. *kaporeth* directly in front of the ארון
aron. *aron*, it's punishable by divine death. The question is the middle
phrase מבית לפרוכת mibeis laparoches, *mibeis laporeches*. Does that just go to
the first half of the verse, you shall not come? Or does
that even go on the second half of the verse, if you
come מבית לפרוכת mibeis laparoches? *mibeis laporeches* ולא ימות *veloy amus*, it's
punishable by divine death? So that is the debate.
פרוכת *Paroches* and פרוכת
*paroches* is the curtain, the veil that separated the קודש Kodesh *Kodesh*
and the קודש Kodesh הקדשים *Kodesh Hakodashim*. The כפורת kaporet, *kaporeth* is
the gold roof on top of the ארון aron, *aron*. The כרובים
*keruvim* were the כפורת *kaporeth*... the כרובים *keruvim* were built off of
the כפורת *kaporeth*.
You have to be right facing
the ארון aron, *aron*, front and center facing the ארון aron *aron*,
not just entering the קודש Kodesh, הקדשים *Kodesh Hakodashim*. Okay, so that's
the whole debate. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says so it's how
to read that פסוק pasuk. *pasuk*. רבנן Rabbanan סברי *Rabbanan savri*, the
rabbis hold, אל el הקדש בלא יבא *el hakodesh belo yavo* is
the prohibition you shall not come refers to the קדש *Kodesh* וההיכל
*vehaheichal*. מבית לפרוכת ועל פני הכפורת pnei hakaporet *mibeis laporeches ve'al penei
hakaporeth*, the other two phrases of that verse, behind the curtain or
in front of the ארון aron? *aron*, ולא ימות *veloy amus*, that
is that is punishable by divine death. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda סבר
*Rabbi Yehuda savar*, Rabbi Yehuda breaks up the verse differently. אל el
הקדש ומבית לפרוכת בלא יבא *el hakodesh umibeis laporeches belo yavo*, into
the sanctuary, the היכל Heichal. *Heichal*, and behind the curtain, that is
a negative prohibition you shall not come. ועל פני הכפורת pnei hakaporet
בלא ימות *ve'al penei hakaporeth belo yamuth*, but only when you face
the ארון aron *aron* is that the punishment of and he shall
not die. Okay, so it's a simple question of how do you
read the middle verse, middle phrase. מאי טעמא mai ta'ama, דרבנן *Mai
ta'ama derabbanan*, now softening that of course the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
if it's just a question about where to put the commas in
the verse, there's gotta be something that influences one read over another
read. So what motivates the rabbis to put the comma where they
put? מאי טעמא דרבנן *Mai ta'ama derabbanan*? אי סלקא דעתך כדקאמר רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Ei salka dach'tach kedekamar Rabbi Yehuda*, if Rabbi Yehuda
was right, now it does not speak about a largest sort of
philosophical or religious sort of perspective which informs it, but a simple
question about redundancy of the verse. אי סלקא דעתך כדקאמר רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda *Ei salka dach'tach kedekamar Rabbi Yehuda*, if it was like
Rabbi Yehuda said that you only get מיתה misa *misa* when you
are facing the ארון aron *aron*, so therefore the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*
is redundant. לכתוב רחמנא אל el הקדש ועל פני הכפורת pnei hakaporet
*Lichtov rachamana el hakodesh ve'al penei hakaporeth*. Let the Torah say do
not enter into the קודש Kodesh *Kodesh* and then you would be
transgressed and do not face the ארון aron? *aron* and you would
get מיתה misa. *misa*. And you don't need to say right what
the status is when you enter into the קודש Kodesh הקדשים *Kodesh
Hakodashim* because according to Rabbi Yehuda entering the קודש kodesh. הקדשים *Kodesh
Hakodashim* is no worse than entering into the היכל Heichal *Heichal*. So
if you already said don't enter the היכל Heichal, *Heichal*, why would
you have to say don't enter the קודש הקדשים *Kodesh Hakodashim*? No
wait, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* will get to that, the opposite argument
for the רבנן For Rabbanan, *Rabbanan*. There's going to be some redundancy
in this verse. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says ולא בעי
מבית לפרוכת *velo ba'ei mibeis laporeches*, you don't have to mention the
קודש הקדשים *Kodesh Hakodashim*. ואנא אמינא *Va'ana amina*, I would have said
היכל Heichal, מיחייב *Heichal michayev*, if you're liable
a negative prohibition just by entering the היכל Heichal, *Heichal*, מבית לפרוכת
מיבעיא *mibeis laporeches mibaya*, why do you have to say that you
also transgress when you go into the קודש הקדשים *Kodesh Hakodashim*?
So מבית לפרוכת דכתב רחמנא
למה לי *mibeis laporeches dechsav rachamana lama li*,
why is the Torah saying don't go into the קודש הקדשים *Kodesh
Hakodashim* behind the curtain? שמע מינה Shma mina, במיתה *shma mina bemisa*,
to tell you that even that is enough to get מיתה misa
*misa* because if it was just say a negative prohibition it's redundant.
Now of course the opposite argument could be made to the rabbis,
some phrase here is going to be redundant. If there are two
areas and three phrases, one of those phrases is extra. Okay, so
that's what Rabbi Yehuda says. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda*, Rabbi
Yehuda would
say back אי כתב רחמנא אל הקדש *ei kesav rachamana el hakodesh*,
if it had just said אל הקדש
*el hakodesh* which means the היכל Heichal, *Heichal*, ולא כתב מבית לפרוכת
*vilo kesav mibeis laporeches*, and it had not said do not enter
into the קודש הקדשים *Kodesh Hakodashim*, הוה אמינא *hava amina*, I would
have thought מאי קדש *mai kodesh*, what does it mean by don't
go into the קודש *Kodesh*? Maybe I would have thought that meant
מבית לפרוכת *mibeis laporeches*, if I would have interpreted that phrase of
קודש *Kodesh* to mean the קודש הקדשים *Kodesh Hakodashim*. אבל היכל heichal
לאו lav נמי לא *aval Heichal lav nami lo*, I would have
thought that the היכל heichal *Heichal* wouldn't have been prohibited at all.
So since the Torah wanted to prohibit the היכל *Heichal* and for
some reason wanted to use the word קודש *Kodesh*, it didn't say
like אהל מועד Ohel Moed *Ohel Moed*, so since it was so
in order to make it clear that קודש *Kodesh* means היכל *Heichal*,
it had to add the clarifying phrase of
קודש הקדשים *Kodesh Hakodashim*, מבית לפרוכת *mibeis laporeches*. then of course קודש
קדשים Kodesh Kodashim. is superfluous, once היכל is prohibited, of course קודש
קדשים Kodesh Kodashim. is prohibited.
That's רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, that's how רב יהודה Rav Yehuda defends
himself. For רבנן Rabbanan and the rabbis would say back, כולהו מצי
למסמך, kulo masi lemismach, you could we would never have gotten confused
that קודש meant קודש קדשים. Kodesh Kodashim, קודש clearly would have meant
היכל. דהיכל כוליה איקרי קודש, D'Heichal kulei ikrei Kodesh, we know the
היכל is called קודש, שנאמר והבדילה הפרוכת לכם בין הקודש ובין קודש
הקדשים. shene'emar v'hivdila haparoches lachem bein hakodesh u'vein kodesh hakodashim. The פרוכת
separates between the simply the holy and the holy of holies. So
simply the phrase קודש clearly refers to היכל, it doesn't need any
greater context or clarification. Okay so the rabbis say why do we
not like רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, because מבית לפרוכת according to him
is superfluous. Once you can't go into the היכל, certainly you can't
go into the קודש קדשים. Kodesh Kodashim Now the גמרא Gemara is
going to reverse the argument for רב יהודה. Rav Yehuda. רב יהודה
מאי טעמא? Rav Yehuda mai ta'ama? What's רב יהודה's Rav Yehuda reasoning
that he doesn't read the verse like the חכמים? Chachamim? אי סלקא
דעתך כחכמי רבנן, I salka da'atcha k'chachamei Rabbanan, if like the rabbis
said
that you get מיתה misa as soon as you enter the קודש
קדשים, Kodesh Kodashim, ליכתוב רחמנא אל הקודש
ומבית לפרוכת. lichtov rachmana el hakodesh u'mibeis laparoches. Say don't go into
the היכל, that's a לאו and don't go into the קודש קדשים
Kodesh Kodashim that then you get מיתה. misa, But once I get
מיתה misa. for going into the קודש קדשים, Kodesh Kodashim why does
it also have to tell me I get מיתה misa. for being
in front of the ארון? aron Of course! Okay? ולא בעיא פני
הכפורת, V'lo ba'ya p'nei hakaporeis,
you don't need to say that do not be directly in front
of the ארון. aron, דאנא אמינא, D'ana amina, I would have said,
מבית לפרוכת דמיתה, d'misa, if when you're in the קודש קדשים Kodesh
Kodashim, you get מיתה, misa. על פני הכפורת מיבעיא? al p'nei hakaporeis
miba'ya? Certainly if you're just in front of the ארון, Aron. it's
only if you're also in front of the ארון, Aron. of course
you get מיתה. misa So that phrase according to you the rabbis
of directly in front of ארון Aron. is superfluous because as soon
as you're in the קודש קדשים Kodesh Kodashim, you get מיתה. Okay.
על פני הכפורת דכתב רחמנא למה לי? Al p'nei hakaporeis d'chasav rachmana
lam-li? Why does the תורה Torah have to say do not be
directly in front of the ארון? Aron שמע shema מינה, על פני
הכפורת מיתה. al p'nei hakaporeis misa. To tell you only when you're
directly in front of the ארון Aron. do you get מיתה. מבית
לפרוכת, if you're just in the קודש קדשים, Kodesh Kodashim. באזהרה, b'azhara,
it's a simple negative prohibition. So how do the rabbis defend themselves,
if you get מיתה as soon as you enter the קודש קדשים,
Kodesh Kodashim why does the תורה Torah emphasize מבית לפרוכת? רבנן, rabbanan
what would the rabbis say? הכא נמי דלא צריך. Hacha nami d'lo
tzarich. You know what, הכא נמי hacha nami you're right. Okay you
gotta love the word הכא נמי. hacha nami. The translation of הכא
נמי hacha nami in this context is דאקא. daka. Okay? So דאקא,
daka, you know, okay
you're right, you don't need
it to say don't be in front of the ארון Aron
as a logical reasoning you would have known it from the other
phrase.
No, no, no, but we're going to say why you need it,
but you don't need it to tell me you're חייב מיתה. chayav
misa.
It's true, you're חייב מיתה chayav misa as soon as you enter
the קודש קדשים. So why did the תורה Torah say it? דהאי
דכתב רחמנא פני הכפורת, D'hai d'chasav rachmana p'nei hakaporeis, so why did
the תורה Torah say do not be in front of the ארון?
Aron למעוטי דרך משופש L'mivti derech meshupash
to tell you only when you come directly in front of the
ארון Aron as opposed to if you enter in an indirect way.
What does an indirect way mean? Let's take a look. כדתניא דבי
רבי אליעזר בן יעקב, Kid'tanya d'bei Rav Eliezer ben Yaakov, like the
ברייתא Baraisa of רב אליעזר בן יעקב, Rav Eliezer ben Yaakov, על
פני הכפורת קדמה, al p'nei hakaporeis keidma,
now this is talking about the sprinkling of on יום כיפור Yom
Kippur towards the again the same phrase פני הכפורת, pnei hakaporet the
face of the כפורת to the east. So זה בנין אב, zeh
binyan av, this is a paradigm, כל מקום שנאמר פני, kol makom
shene'emar p'nei, when it says the face, אינו אלא פני קדים, eino
ela p'nei kadim, it means the eastern face. Okay, which by the
way is true in the directions of the תורה. Torah. The תורה
Torah always assumes that a person when it's describing directions is facing
the east because people face the rising sun. Hence the phrase to
orient yourself, which means to point yourself towards the orient, towards the
east. Right? As opposed to occident yourself which would be to point
yourself to the west.
Anyway, yeah. So right. So see that?
So
for example, that's why the תורה, Torah, what are the words of
the תורה Torah for south is תימנה. teimana. Why is south תימנה?
teimana? Because תימנה teimana is ימין. yamin. If you're facing the east,
your right hand is the south. Okay, so we assume a person
and the פנים panim is the east and אחור achor is the
west. So פני הכפורת pnei hakaporet means the east face of the
כפורת. Okay? So when אברהם Avraham says to לוט, Lot, אם השמאל
ואימינה ואם הימין ואשמאילה, im hasmol v'eimina v'im hayamin v'asme'ila,
he meant if you go south I'll go north if you go
north I'll go south. Okay? When the תורה Torah says אחרי דרך
מבוא השמש, acharei derech mivo hashemesh, it means מבוא השמש mivo hashemesh
is the west, right, the setting of the sun, and אחרי acharei
is the opposite of קדים, kadim, it's אחור, achor, it's westward. So
אחרי דרך מבוא השמש acharei derech mivo hashemesh means westward towards the
setting sun. Just so you should know your biblical direction. So קדים
kadim therefore
what?
Exactly. So anyway פני הכפורת קדמה p'nei hakaporeis keidma means east. Okay,
that's very interesting. What does that have to do with us? אינו
אלא פני קדים. Eino ela p'nei kadim. Now
what does that have to do with us? So רש"י Rashi says
what that means is, is that if you enter into the קודש
קדשים not facing the ארון, Aron. through a backdoor, you dig a
tunnel and you enter in through the side or through the back,
you know you come up from the bottom of the ground. Then
you would not be חייב מיתה. chayav mita. So the reason it
says פני pnei, הכפורת means you have to enter in through the
front door as it were facing the ארון. Aron רש״י Rashi even
goes so far as to suggest let's say you enter in but
your face is not facing the ארון. Aron, You enter in like
at an angle or you enter in walking backwards into it that
there also you might not be חייב מיתה chayav mita because you're
not entering facing the ארון. Aron,
So that's what the פני הכפורת tells me. Without פני הכפורת I
know you're חייב chayav as soon as you enter in. The reason
it says פני הכפורת is not to tell me you have to
be in front of the ארון Aron. but to tell me you're
only חייב chayav when you enter in facing the ארון. Aron. So
if you enter in walking backwards or at an angle or through
a side door or tunnel you would not be חייב. chayav.
So the implication is intent? Is that right?
No, it's how you walk in.
How you walk in, when's that important?
No, it's just the physical reality. Are you facing this way? Are
you walking backwards? Are you coming through the side? But you have
to enter facing the ארון Aron. to be חייב. chayav. Yeah.
Is there a ראיה raya for רש״י? Rashi? Because the לויים Leviim
in the משכן Mishkan always would go in backwards to take apart
the...
well no, but the תורה Torah actually says that the כהנים Kohanim
go in and they take it apart and then the לויים Leviim
can come in. Well it doesn't say that in the... in the
תורה. Torah.
It just says that the כהנים Kohanim will go in and they
will cover it up. Okay but anyway you're thinking about נח׳ס Noach's
sons.
All
right anyway רש״י Rashi says they entered in backwards. Okay anyway so
the גמרא gemara says like this. So that... now how is this
at all relevant to us? That was all a very fascinating debate.
How is it relevant to us? So let's take a look at
what the גמרא gemara says. Okay, oh well first let's finish up
this debate. רבי יהודה ואימא קרא פני. Rabbi Yehuda ve'eima kra pnei.
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says if all it wanted to tell us
was that you have to enter in facing in the you know
eastward, let it say the פני, the face. מאי אל, אל פני?
mai el, el pnei? שמע מינה
אל דווקא. shma mina el davka. אל means directly in front of
the ארון Aron, and this is where it's critical to us. So
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says אל פני הכפורת el pnei hakaporet means
not just in that direction, that general direction, but it means אל
פני el pnei directly in front of the ארון Aron, and only
then am I חייב מיתה. chayav mita. So the upshot of this
lovely debate for us is whether when the תורה Torah says
towards means exactly in that direction or in the general vicinity. So
the רבנן rabbanan. say אל means the general vicinity, you're חייב מיתה
chayav mita and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says אל means directly in
front. So similarly when it says sprinkle towards the קודש or the
קודש קודשים, Kodesh Kodashim, does it mean directly in that you know
exactly in that direction or general vicinity? And that's our debate of
the sprinkling. So let's take a look. רבי יהודה דאמר פני הכפורת
דווקא. Rabbi Yehuda de'amar pnei hakaporet davka.
So now רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
says that פני הכפורת means exactly in that direction and directly in
front of the ארון. Aron. והזה אל נוכח ve'hiza el nochach when
it says by the פרה אדומה, Para Aduma, he shall sprinkle towards
פני אהל מועד, pnei ohel moed, it means דנמי דווקא denami davka
exactly. So then that the פרה אדומה Para Aduma would not be
כשר kasher if it was not exactly in that direction. ולרבנן Ulerabbanan
and the rabbis would say מי דהתם לאו דווקא, mi dehatam lav
davka, since it doesn't mean exactly in front of the ארון aron.
when it talks about entering in, so הכא נמי לאו דווקא hacha
nami lav davka when it talks about sprinkling towards the... the היכל,
the you know the אהל מועד
by the פרה אדומה Para Aduma doesn't mean exactly, it means in
that general direction. Okay that explains why they argue about פרה אדומה.
Para Aduma. It doesn't explain why everybody agrees by the other קרבנות
korbanot that it doesn't have to be exactly in that direction. Right?
The גמרא Gemara. says even by יום כיפור Yom Kippur and all
the other inner קרבנות, korbanot, there everybody agrees that if it's not
exactly correct, it's still good. Why is that true? So let's take
a look. מתיב ליה רב יוסף לרב יהודה. mative lei Rav Yosef
le'Rav Yehuda. So רב יוסף Rav Yosef asks רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
who gave this explanation of the debate about sprinkling. מכדי אל דווקא.
michdei el davka. If you're going to say that רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda says אל or towards means exactly,
so על נמי דווקא. al nami davka.
So first of all I've got a problem. When the תורה... Torah...
and then when the תורה Torah says you should do the sprinkling
on יום כיפור Yom Kippur on the ארון, aron רבי יהודה Rebbi
Yehuda would say it means literally on the ארון, aron? right? So
remember we say one up and seven down. So then it says
you sprinkle on the ארון. aron? רש״י Rashi quotes the פסוק. pasuk
It says על פני הכפורת. You shall sprinkle on the face of
the כפורת, the cover of the ארון. aron? So we always say
it means like in that
direction, the blood doesn't directly hit the cover of the ארון. aron,
But if רבי Rebbe יהודה says it means exactly, why doesn't he
say that means exactly?
ואלא דמקדש
שני דלא הוי ארון וכפורת. ve'ela demikdash sheni delo havei aron vekaporet.
So wouldn't רבי Rabbi יהודה say that in the second בית המקדש
Beit Hamikdash where there was no ארון, aron. הכא נמי דלא עביד
הזאה hacha nami delo avid haza'ah he wouldn't do the sprinkling? So
even רבי Rabbi יהודה cannot say that אל and על when it
talks about sprinkling always means exactly in this way. So אמר רבא
בר עולא אמר קרא amar Rava bar Ulla amar kra no. Regarding
when there's a בית מקדש שני, Beit Hamikdash Sheni, the פסוק pasuk
says וכיפר את מקדש הקודש vechiper et mikdash hakodesh that אהרן Aharon
will sanctify the sanctuary of the holy place. So that's a little
redundant, מקדש הקודש. mikdash hakodesh. And that tells you מקום המקודש לקודש,
makom hamikudash lakodesh, the place that is sanctified even if it doesn't
have all the vessels there. So there there's a special פסוק psuk
to. include the idea of even without the ארון, aron. but basically
רבי יהודה says that the פסוקים psukim mean what they say with
a little variation there in terms of the presence of the ארון.
aron. The פסוקים psukim are exact. So that's the debate by the
פרה אדומה, Parah Adumah, do you have to sprinkle it exactly towards
the מקדש Mikdash or not? And presumably for some reason that's not
going to be an issue by the other קרבנות. korbonot. Okay, although
the גמרא Gemara does not exactly spell out why it would not
be an issue by the other korbonot. So that's the first explanation.
Let's take a look at the second explanation. רבא אמר הא והא
רבנן, Rava amar hava ha-rabbanan, actually the question about the sprinkling of
the פרה אדומה Parah Adumah both go according to the רבנן rabbanan.
that generally say that, you know, that you don't need exact. So
you don't need exact by the sprinkling of יום כיפור, Yom Kippur,
it doesn't have to be directly dead center, it could be a
little to the side, as long as it's towards the curtain, it
doesn't have to be directly towards the center. And by the פרה
אדומה Parah Adumah it doesn't have to be directly toward the קודש.
So what about the ברייתא braita that says if it's not directly,
it's not valid by the פרה אדומה? Parah Adumah? So let's take
a look. דהאי da-hai and the question is how what does mean
the general vicinity? How close is close enough? For דף כ"ח עמוד
א', daf kaf-chet amud aleph, so here the issue is האי דקאי
מזרח ומערב ואידי hi dekai mizrach u'maarav va-adi in one case they're
oriented east-west.
You're facing, you know, towards the
מקדש, Mikdash, you're facing if the door is in the east, you
would have to be facing east, right? Yeah. So you is that
right? Or am I getting that confused?
If if the opening is in the east, you and you are
away from it you're further east.
No, you're facing westward. Okay, so you'd have to be facing westward
you're facing westward, you're not exactly in line, you know, it's like
the people that take out their compass before they start שחרית shacharis
to make sure, you know, that they're exactly in line. Nah you
don't need you're generally pointing in the right that yeah course, you're
generally pointing in the right direction, that's enough. That would be good.
How about the ברייתא braita that says that if you're not pointing
at the right direction you're not good by the sprinkling? הא דקאי
צפון ודרום ואידי. ha-dekai tzafon ve-darom va-adi. That's when you're facing north-south,
you're totally off. Okay, so if you're totally off-face, you're not good.
So reasonable question. What you still have to be in the general
direction for at a certain point you're not sprinkling correctly at all.
Okay, now let's finish up the ברייתא. braita. אמר מר, amar mar,
so the master taught we taught in the ברייתא braita before, ושבפנים
ושבמצורע שלא לשמן פסולות. v'she-bifnim v'she-bi-metzora she-lo lishmah psulot. When it talks
about that's about the פרה אדומה. Parah Adumah. How about the other
inner קרבנות? korbonot? The other קרבנות korbonot that are done inside the
מקדש Mikdash like inside the היכל like the goat and the ox
of יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, and, and the מצורע, metzora, the אשם
asham of a מצורע, metzora, we're not talking that's not an inner
חטאת chatas at all, it's an אשם asham but we're talking about
the sprinkling, when you you know you dip the hyssop into sort
of a mixture there by the מצורע metzora and you sprinkle it
so that as well, there we say שלא לשמן פסולות, she-lo lishmah
psulot, if you do it שלא לשמן she-lo lishmah it's invalid because
it's a חטאת chatas and a חטאת chatas done שלא לשמן she-lo
lishmah is invalid. שלא מכוונות כשרות, she-lo mechuvano kashrut, if it's not
directly in the correct direction it's
still kosher. והתניא בין שלא לשמן בין שלא מכוונות כשרות, ve-hatanya bein
she-lo lishmah bein she-lo mechuvano kashrut, don't we have a ברייתא braita
that says even if it's done שלא לשמן she-lo lishmah it's kosher,
which is surprising since it's a חטאת chatas and a חטאת chatas
done שלא לשמן she-lo lishmah other than the מצורע metzora we'll get
to the מצורע metzora in a minute, a חטאת chatas done שלא
לשמן she-lo lishmah is normally פסול. pasul. So אמר רב יוסף לא
קשיא הא רבי אליעזר והא רבנן, amar Reb Yosef lo kashya ha
Reb Eliezer ve-ha rabbanan, it's a debate of רבי אליעזר Reb Eliezer
and the רבנן. rabbanan So actually I'm sorry, I misquoted it. The
statement of שלא לשמן she-lo lishmah is kosher is not about the
חטאת. chatas. Everybody would agree that a חטאת chatas שלא לשמן she-lo
lishmah is invalid. It's about the אשם asham of the מצורע. metzora.
So here we have one ברייתא braita that says the אשם asham
of a מצורע metzora done שלא לשמן she-lo lishmah is invalid, which
is a little bizarre, since when is an אשם asham invalid when
done שלא לשמן? she-lo lishmah? And now we have another ברייתא braita
that says the אשם asham of a מצורע metzora done שלא לשמן
she-lo lishmah is valid. Okay, so here now the answer almost is
obvious, one is רבי אליעזר Reb Eliezer and one is the רבנן.
rabbanan רבי אליעזר דמקיש אשם לחטאת, Reb Eliezer de-makish asham le-chatas, remember
way back in the beginning of זבחים? Zevachim? See this should be
nice, it makes you it shows you how everything constantly folds back
into itself. Okay, so way back at the beginning of זבחים Zevachim
you remember רבי אליעזר Reb Eliezer that said an אשם asham also
comes for sin and therefore even an אשם asham שלא לשמו she-lo
lishmo is invalid, so according to רבי אליעזר Reb Eliezer then an
אשם asham is like a חטאת, chatas, if you do the אשם
asham שלא לשמו she-lo lishmo it's also invalid, whereas according to the
רבנן rabbanan the אשם asham שלא לשמו she-lo lishmo is valid. רבי
אליעזר דמקיש אשם לחטאת. Reb Eliezer de-makish asham le-chatas. Now, the problem
is that we're not just talking about we're talking about the sprinkling.
The sprinkling was not done with the אשם, asham, the sprinkling for
the מצורע metzora was done this week's פרשה parsha with the לוג
log of oil. Okay, you would sprinkle this לוג log of oil.
The פסוק pasuk says
actually פסוק pasuk
remind me again the difference between אשם asham and חטאת. chatas. The
difference between an אשם asham and a חטאת? chatas? What? You want
Pop to hear that? The difference between an אשם asham and a
חטאת? chatas?
An אשם asham and a חטאת chatas both come for sin, a
חטאת chatas actually also comes for purification. An אשם, asham, a חטאת
chatas most often comes for purification,
an אשם asham much more rarely so. Why is there when they
are about sin, why is there a difference? It's hard to exactly
get a handle on that. Some try to say that an אשם
asham is more for the guilt and for the personal experience of
sin, and the חטאת chatas is more for the metaphysical reality of
sin, like the way a חטאת chatas is more about טומאה, tumah,
it sort of addresses the reality of sin that sin has created.
But it is hard to get a good handle on how an
אשם asham is different. Just one second, let me just read you
the פסוק pasuk here from this week's פרשה parsha about the sprinkling
by the מצורע. metzora. The פסוק pasuk says, ולקח הכהן את כבש
האשם. v'lakach hakohen es keves ha'asham.
So there's the אשם. asham. ולוג השמן. v'log hashemen.
And then you slaughter the כבש, keves, which is the אשם. asham.
ולקח הכהן מדם האשם ונתן על תנוך אוזן המטהר הימנית. v'lakach hakohen
midam ha'asham v'nasan al tnuch ozen hamitaher haymanit. You put it on
the guy's ears, etcetera. And then it says, וטבל הכהן את אצבעו
הימנית מן השמן אשר על כפו השמאלית והזה מן השמן באצבעו שבע
פעמים לפני ה'. v'taval hakohen es etzba'o haymanit min hashemen asher al
kapo hasmalit v'hizah min hashemen b'etzba'o sheva pe'amim lifnei Hashem. Sprinkle it
לפני ה' lifnei Hashem toward the היכל לפני ה'. lifnei Hashem.
So the first issue was even if it's not exactly in that
direct כסדר keseder שלא מכוון. shelo mechuvon. Now the question is let's
say that sprinkling was שלא לשמה. shelo lishma. So we're going to
say the status of that sprinkling of the oil is the same
as the status if you did שלא לשמה shelo lishma to the
אשם. asham. So if you say that an אשם asham generally שלא
לשמה shelo lishma is okay because it's not like a חטאת, chatas,
then the sprinkling שלא לשמה shelo lishma is okay. But according to
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that says an אשם asham is like a
חטאת, chatas, so the same way if you did the אשם asham
שלא לשמה shelo lishma it's no good, the sprinkling of the oil
which is connected to the אשם, asham, if that's done שלא לשמה
shelo lishma it's also no good. Let's just finish up to the
משנה. mishna. הרי דרבי אליעזר הרי דרבנן. harei d'Rabbi Eliezer harei d'rabbanan.
רבי אליעזר דמקיש אשם לחטאת. Rabbi Eliezer d'makish asham l'chatas. רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer that links an אשם asham to a חטאת. chatas. מקיש
נמי לוג לאשם. makish nami log l'asham. He links the לוג log
to the אשם. asham. So an אשם asham done שלא לשמה shelo
lishma is invalid, the sprinkling of the oil שלא לשמה shelo lishma
is invalid. רבנן לא מקשי rabbanan lo makshi and the רבנן don't
say an אשם asham is like a חטאת. chatas. So even an
אשם asham שלא לשמה shelo lishma is valid, so the oil meant
שלא לשמה shelo lishma is also valid. So now the גמרא Gemara
says we thought we were, we thought we had escaped this, ולרבי
אליעזר וכי דבר הלמד בהיקש חוזר ומלמד בהיקש? v'l'Rabbi Eliezer v'chi davar
halamad b'hekesh chozer umelamed b'hekesh?
If Michael were here he certainly would have asked that question already.
So one minute, according to רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, is the way
we know an אשם asham is not good שלא לשמה shelo lishma
because it's linked to a חטאת? chatas? But then that's learned out
from a linkage, so that can't teach out based on a linkage.
So it can't teach that the oil also שלא לשמה shelo lishma
is not valid because it itself is only a derived principle. So
that's not going to work. So the גמרא Gemara says אלא אמר
רבא ela amar Rava rather רבא Rava says הא והא רבנן ha
v'ha rabbanan they're both the רבנן that say שלא לשמה shelo lishma
is valid. But what did the first משנה mishna in זבחים Zevachim
teach? A normal קרבן korban done שלא לשמה shelo lishma is valid,
but what's the but? What does the first משנה mishna teach? A
קרבן korban done שלא לשמה shelo lishma is valid, but it does
not עלה לבעלים לשם חובה. alah l'bealim l'shem chova. Thank you Michael,
came in right at the right time. It does not count for
the owners, they don't get credit. So if this מצורע metzora brings
his אשם asham and it's שלא לשמה, shelo lishma, right, or the
oil is sprinkled שלא לשמה, shelo lishma, what's the principle? It's valid,
means I can eat the meat, I can eat the remainder of
the oil, but I don't get credit for it. Now if the
מצורע metzora doesn't get credit, it means it does not satisfy his
purification process. So the ברייתא braita that says it's invalid means he's
not טהור. tahor. If he wants to become טהור tahor he has
to bring another one. The ברייתא braita that says it's valid means
you can eat the meat, you can eat the remainder of the
oil. In terms of the object of the קרבן korban it's still
valid, but it didn't satisfy the goals it was out to serve.
So let's just הא והא רבנן כאן להכשיר, ha v'ha rabbanan kan
l'hachshir, one is coming to actually validate the קרבן korban that you
do achieve when you do it שלא לשמה. shelo lishma. כאן להרצות,
kan l'hartzos, the other is to make it desirable, meaning to achieve
its goals, and it has not achieved its goals, and therefore the
מצורע metzora needs to bring another one in order to be good.
So with this we end this whole digression about the sprinkling in
the right direction because the משנה mishna talked about the number of
sprinkles מעכב זה את זה. meakev zeh es zeh. Then we got
into this whole discussion about the direction of the sprinkling. But now
we are going to get back to the major theme, which is
things that consist of different component parts if all the parts are
interdependent. Yes.
למי בעי למיכוון? l'mi ba'ei l'michuven?
The person who determines what, whether it was שלא לשמה? shelo lishma?
Yeah. That gets back to the whole old discussions. We're assuming that
לשמה lishma means it was articulated לשמה, lishma, not just thought. But
that's an issue we've had from the very beginning.
למי בעי למיכוון? l'mi ba'ei l'michuven? Or the person who...
Well, that's the question also. The self-reporting. Yeah.
We didn't have none of that discussed.
Okay, now
we אדך, adach, we turn away at least from קרבנות. korbanos. We
already turned away a little, we started mentioning... and so on, but
now we are really going to start leaving קרבנות korbanot in the
dust and for the first thing we look at is the כלי
המקדש. klei hamikdash. So if you remember the earlier ברייתא baraita went
in a numerical order. First it talked about, you know, the two
different types of the two loaves of bread, then it talked about
the three things that you need for the פרה אדומה, parah adumah,
the four מינים minim of the לולב, lulav, the four things that
you need for, you know,
for the, what do you call, for the מצורע, metzora, then it
talked about the seven sprinklings. So we're still in the seven mode.
Okay, so now let's take a look. שבעה קני מנורה מעכבין זה
את זה, sheva kanei menorah me'akvin zeh et zeh, the seven branches
of the מנורה menorah prevent one another from being valid. If you
have a מנורה menorah with only six branches or fewer, it's not
a valid מנורה. menorah. You can't be like, oh, well, light the
other branches. No, you need it all there. Let's
see... we'll talk about that. שבעה נרותיה מעכבין זה את זה, sheva
neroteha me'akvin zeh et zeh, the seven lamps. Right? The branches is
the physical thing. In the top of each branch, you would put
a, you know, a little type of a vessel that you would
fill with oil. That would be called the lamp, the נר. ner.
The נר ner is not the flame. The נר ner is the
little, okay, you got a picture. I'm going to hand out a
picture in a minute. Okay, well might as well hand out the
picture now.
So I have uploaded it, the Jam, I, or if you can
see, I'd uploaded it there, which is why we started a little
bit late. I wanted you to have it. I know, everybody that
has Artscroll is blessed with a picture already. Okay, they of course
took it from the same source that I stole it from, which
is this wonderful book called
המשכן, hamishkan, תבנית המשכן וכליו. tavnit hamishkan v'keilav. Anytime anybody's learning ויקרא,
vayikra, whatever you call it, תרומה, terumah, תצוה, tetzaveh, it's great and
then we have to put nice little pictures, you know, that goes
through all the different opinions and so on.
Okay, so Jed, you should be able... you said you don't see
it? I am sorry. Let me pop it up. Actually your picture
is nicer
than the one in the Artscroll.
Oh,
there we go.
I know there was a...
well, according to one opinion it looked like that. There were a
couple of other... there were a bunch of other opinions.
Look at that curve. They're very, very different.
I am going to
talk about that in a minute. I am going to talk about
straight versus...
I like this. Especially on this side, over
here, you see different, okay. Let me play around with this. Okay,
so מנורות menorot that...
no,
no, two opinions. So let me actually say one thing here.
Let me say, let me say one thing about this. Of course,
in our vision, it's always like these arched is a picture. However,
רמב"ם rambam assumes because none of the descriptions of מנורה menorah say
it arched, it says the branches come out. So רמב"ם rambam assumes
it means straight lines. So this is actually the actual picture with
the רמב"ם's rambam hand, a Leonardo da Vinci of the מנורה menorah
from his original manuscript. Okay, and here is just a like redone,
you know, for us, you know, in order to be a little
more readable. But the רמב"ם rambam drew this picture. The רמב"ם rambam
understood that they were these sharp angles. We now know that that
was clearly not true. Titus's arch depicts a מנורה menorah of, of,
you know, curved arches. And in the Burnt House, anybody ever go
to the Burnt House exhibit right near the כותל? kotel? In the
Burnt House, which obviously they were overseeing there, they were כהנים, kohanim,
they have, you know, engravings of the מנורה menorah and they are
arched branches. Okay.
That's actually a big debate in academia because of the prohibition of
creating facsimiles and people understood that as proof that it's actually...
oh give me a break.
Right. It is the must of academia to... nah, you can... I
don't buy that at all. You know where it's a debate to
do that? In the rabbinic literature. I don't think the כהנים kohanim
there had held that and that it was just drawing, it was
a problem. In fact, actually creating it three-dimensional... I don't buy that
for a minute. Anyway, all the other contemporary evidence that we have
shows a מנורה menorah with arches, not with straight lines. Okay, so
let's take a look. The seven branches are מעכבין זה את זה.
me'akvin zeh et zeh. So if you only... that's... the seven נרות.
nerot. If you look at the top you see these little vessels,
you know, that you actually put the oil and the wicks in,
that sit on top of the branches, are מעכבין זה את זה.
me'akvin zeh et zeh. If you don't have them all, you don't
do any of them. And now we get to stuff that applies
to us on a regular basis.
שתי פרשיות שבמזוזה מעכבין זו את זו, shtei parshiot shebamzuza me'akvin zu
et zu, שמע Shema, and והיה אם שמוע v'hayah im shamoa hold
back one another. If you only have one פרשה, parsha, you're not...
you don't have a good מזוזה. mezuza. Not only that, אפילו כתב
אחד מעכב, afilu ktav echad me'akve, even one letter holds it up.
If one letter is wrong in your מזוזה, mezuza, the whole מזוזה
mezuza is invalid.
ארבע פרשיות שבתפילין מעכבין זו את זו.
arba parshiot shebitfillin
me'akvin zu et zu.
We're already in numerical.
Yeah, I know, it's very interesting. I don't know why it works
that it went from two to seven and then it goes back
and starts going up again. And now it's turning itself to very
practical things, and maybe that's why. You know, the only really practical
thing we mentioned before was the לולב, lulav, which okay is practical,
but there's a whole פרק perek in סוכה sukkah that discusses how
you do the לולב. lulav. There's nowhere else in ש"ס shas where
it discusses תפילין, tfillin, ציצית tzitzit and מזוזה. mezuza. And this is
at the very...
well, sometimes we find an excuse to bring things in.
We're not going to devote an entire מסכת masechet to it. So
here is where רבי found the place to introduce the discussion of
תפילין, tefillin, ציצית, tzitzis, and מזוזה, mezuzah, and that's why I believe
the numbering starts again because it's like, now let's take it again
from the beginning, from the two and the four and whatever, and
talk about some practical things. Okay, and this is where the shift
becomes. So, what? Yeah. So, ארבע פרשיות שבטפילין מעכבין זו את זו,
Arba parshiot she-ba-tefillin me-akvin zu et zu, the four פרשיות, parshiot, שמע,
והיה אם שמוע, Ve-haya im shamo'a, and the two פרשיות parshiot that
talk about קדש לי Kadesh li and והיה כי יביאך Ve-haya ki
yevi'acha that also talk about putting on תפילין, tefillin, all
of those are required, אפילו כתב אחד מעכבן, afillu ketav echad me-akvan,
even one letter holds them back from being valid.
ארבע ציציות מעכבות זו את זו, Arba tzitzit me-akvot zu et zu,
all four ציציות tzitzit at the four corners of the בגד beged
prevent the others from being, you can't say I've done three quarters
of the מצוה mitzvah because I've got it on three corners. However,
שהן מצוה אחת, she-hen mitzvah achat, they all are one מצוה mitzvah
of a בגד beged with ציצית. tzitzit. It's not four separate מצות.
mitzvot. רבי ישמעאל אומר ארבעתן ארבע מצות, Rabbi Yishmael omer arbatan arba
mitzvot, they are four מצות. mitzvot. What does that mean according to
Rabbi Yishmael? Do I get two מצות mitzvot for putting ציצית tzitzis
on two of my corners? We will see in the גמרא. Gemara
But now we are going to, after we have a nice little
גמרא Gemara that discusses both practical issues of the מנורה Menorah and
also some אגדתא Agaddata of the מנורה, Menorah, we are then going
to start turning to תפילין tefillin and מזוזה mezuzah and so on.
So we start today with מנורה. Menorah.
Yeah, so at least right now for Rabbi Yishmael, we're trying to
say that he still agrees, we just, let's hold that off.
Okay, so let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. מאי טעמא, what
is the reason that you need all of the seven branches? הויה
כתיב בה, havaya ketiv bah, it says הויה, havaya, it says כפתוריה
וקנתיה ממנה יהיו, kaftoreha u-kenoteha mimena yihyu, shall be, shall be means
exactly this way. תנו רבנן, tanu rabbanan, we taught in a ברייתא,
braita, מנורה היתה באה מן העשת, Menorah hayta ba-ah min ha-eshet, the
מנורה Menorah came from a lump of ore, of gold, meaning that
it was not made by pieces and melded together, it was beaten
from one large...
A what? גוש
מתכת, gush matechet, a lump of metal, thank you.
ומן הזהב, u-min ha-zahav, and it was golden. עשאה מן הגרוטאות, as'ah
min ha-gruta'ot, if you made it from individual pieces even if you
melded them, פסולה, psula, it's invalid. But משאר מיני מתכות, mi-shear minei
matechot, if it's not from gold, כשרה, kshera, that is valid. The
גמרא's Gemara going to learn it out from פסוקים, psukim, but of
course they although have historical evidence because there is clear historical evidence
that the חשמונאים Chashmonaim when they rededicated the מקדש Mikdash started with
a מנורה Menorah that was not gold. We'll see what metal it
was in a minute, but they know so gold is not מעכב,
me-akev, but the idea of one piece of metal is מעכב. me-akev.
מאי שנא מן הגרוטאות פסולה, mai shna min ha-gruta'ot psula, why from
different pieces that are melded together is that invalid? דכתיב, de-chtiv, the
פסוק pasuk, says מקשה, miksha, beaten, דהויה, de-havaya, and it says "it
shall be". Okay, so the meaning it shall be again this way.
שאר מיני מתכות נמי זהב והויה, shear minei matechot nami zahav ve-havaya,
but how about other metals? It also says it shall be gold
and it says shall be, so let's say it has to be
exactly gold.
So the גמרא Gemara says, so no, אמר קרא תעשה, amar kra
te-aseh, shall be made, which means that there's a certain amount of
latitude, any way you make it. לרבות שאר מיני מתכות, le-rabot shear
minei matechot, that other metals are okay. So the גמרא Gemara obviously
says how are you going to decide what to include and what
to exclude? ואימא לרבות גרוטאות, ve-eima le-rabot gruta'ot, maybe it's coming to
include even individual pieces melded together. לא סלקא דעתך, lo salka datach,
that doesn't make sense. דהמקשה כתיב הויה, de-ha-miksha ketiv havaya, the word
"shall be" is written on beaten.
Why, what does the פסוק pasuk, say? It says, as Rashi quotes
it,
מקשה תעשה את המנורה, miksha te-aseh et ha-menorah, מקשה miksha you shall
make, no that's not הויה, havaya, what does it say? It says
ועשית מנורת זהב טהור מקשה תעשה המנורה ירכה וקנה גביעיה כפתוריה ופרחיה
ממנה יהיו. Ve-asita menorat zahav tahor miksha te-aseh ha-menorah yerekha ve-kanah gevieiha
kaftoreha u-feracheiha mimena yihyu. So the יהיו yihyu comes after the מקשה
miksha and it's further away from זהב. zahav. The first clause says
gold, beaten, shall be, so the shall be is closer to the
word beaten than it is to the word gold. Okay, by a
few words.
And the גמרא Gemara says לא סלקא דעתך דהמקשה כתיב הויה, lo
salka datach de-ha-miksha ketiv havaya, the word shall be is closer to
the word beaten.
תעשה נמי אמקשה כתיב, te-aseh nami a-miksha ktiv, it says מקשה תעשה,
miksha te-aseh, and תעשה te-aseh is coming to expand the possibilities, why
not read it as saying it doesn't have to be beaten, but
other ways are also good, why not?
תעשה נמי אמקשה כתיב, te-aseh nami a-miksha ktiv, מקשה מקשה לעכב, miksha
miksha le-akev, no, it says מקשה miksha twice. It says מקשה תעשה
המנורה miksha te-aseh ha-menorah and then it says מקשה יהיו. miksha yihyu.
It repeats that it must be beaten, that you can't vary.
Keep on reading, keep on reading, not that פסוק, pasuk
later, it says at the very end of it, it
says כפתוריה וקנתיה kaftoreha u-kenoteha ממנה יהיו כלה מקשה
אחת
זהב טהור.
mimena yihyu kula miksha achat
zahav tahor.
So it says מקשה miksha twice, that which... cannot compromise.
Okay, so גמרא Gemara says זהב זהב נמי לאיקוש. zahav zahav nami
l'eikush. It says gold twice as well at the beginning and at
the end. Then the גמרא Gemara says האי מאי, hai mai, one
minute. אי אמרת בשלמא מן הגרוטאות פסולה, ei amarta bishlama min ha-grutaot
pesula, if you say that milled-it from individual pieces is invalid ומשאר
מיני מתכות כשרה u-mish'ar minei matachot keshera but other metals is okay,
that's the split, היינו זהב זהב מקשה מקשה לדרשה. hainu zahav zahav
miksha miksha lidrasha. Then I understand why it repeats the word gold
and beaten, because it's going to come to explain to include certain
things. We'll see that in a minute. Okay, so we have to
wait to see what the גמרא Gemara, means. אלא אי אמרת מן
הגרוטאות כשרה ella ei amarta min ha-grutaot keshera ומשאר מיני מתכות פסולה,
u-mish'ar minei matachot pesula, but if you say that pieces is valid
and other metals are not valid, זהב זהב מקשה מקשה מאי דרשת
ביה? zahav zahav miksha miksha mai darashta beih? Then there is not
you're not going to have anything to do with these extra words.
So the גמרא Gemara is going to say because of economy of
word, only way we can explain how to deal with all of
the extra word is just say that other metals are okay but
different pieces are not good. Now what how do we have to
use what how are we going to use the other word? That's
the גמרא Gemara says right now. Actually we can't say the what
I'm sorry, but let's just see how it uses the other word.
The גמרא Gemara says okay but well you don't we can't understand
it till we read the next sentences. Okay, מאי דרשת ביה? mai
darashta beih? says the גמרא, Gemara says מאי
דרשה, mai drasha, what is this דרשה drasha you're referring to? דתניא:
detanya: כיכר זהב טהור יעשה אותה, kikar zahav tahor ya'aseh otah, one
כיכר kikar of gold you shall make it, את כל הכלים האלה,
et kol hakeilim ha'eileh, with all the vessels. בא זהב, ba zahav,
so if it's gold, then all of the requirements apply. באה כיכר,
ba'ah kikar, it have to be a כיכר kikar of gold which
is a certain weight. אינה באה זהב אינה באה כיכר, eina ba'ah
zahav eina ba'ah kikar, if it's not gold, then the amount of
metal you use does not matter. גביעיה כפתוריה ופרחיה, gvi'eiha kaftoreiha u'feracheiha,
it have to have these cups, flower, and the sort of sphere
and flowers. Similarly, באה זהב באה גביעים כפתורים ופרחים, ba'ah zahav ba'ah
gvi'im kaftorim u'ferachim, when it's gold, you need all of these ornaments,
the cups, the spheres, and the flowers, a number of right. אינה
באה זהב אינה באה גביעים כפתורים ופרחים, eina ba'ah zahav eina ba'ah
gvi'im kaftorim u'ferachim, without gold you don't need all of these ornaments.
Okay now the גמרא Gemara says just to finish this and then
we'll go back and explain how this all fits in. ואימא נמי,
ve'eima nami, why don't we also say: באה זהב באה קנים? ba'ah
zahav ba'ah kanim? if it's gold then you need to have seven
sort of arms. אינה באה זהב אינה באה קנים. eina ba'ah zahav
eina ba'ah kanim. No, if it's not gold you don't even need
it to be a seven branched מנורה, menorah, you can just have
like one branch. So the גמרא Gemara says no, הוא פומיט מקרי,
hu pumit mikrei, that's not called a מנורה, menorah, that's called a
lamp.
Okay so so okay maybe
for all right I don't know why, but that's how the גמרא
Gemara learns. Okay now so how does this fit in to what
we said before?
Well let's first finish the list of things that are required as
a result of it being gold. וזה מעשה המנורה מקשה זהב, vezeh
ma'aseh hamenorah miksha zahav, beaten of gold. באה זהב באה מקשה, ba'ah
zahav ba'ah miksha, if it's gold it has to be one beaten
unit. אינה באה זהב אינה באה מקשה, eina ba'ah zahav eina ba'ah
miksha, and however if it is not come gold it is does
not have to be beaten, so actually this whole idea that it
has to be a one unit is only when it's gold. So
the basic point is like this: when it's gold you have all
the requirements: one unit, the גביעים, gvi'im, the כפתורים, kaftorim, the weight,
all of that. When it's not gold you have a much more
latitude as long as it's got seven branches. Now how does this
fit in to the גמרא Gemara before? Because the גמרא Gemara before
says like this: look. If we say like we do say that
you can use other metals, then you'll understand why the פסוקים psukim
have to talk about say you know it says מקשה miksha twice
and it says gold twice. Because what the thing is like this,
it's saying when you use gold, it's repeating things like מקשה miksha
and so on to say all of these requirements are necessary. When
you use other metals, then these requirements are not so necessary. That
I understand. But if you were to take the opposite position you're
suggesting, which is it has to be gold, but it doesn't have
to be you know sort of a one unit, it could be
milled did, then that doesn't make sense. Then you're going to
say like if it's
מקשה miksha then
it have to be
gold,
if
it's not מקשה miksha you would say it also has to be
gold, so you can't understand why the פסוקים psukim are linking the
gold to the מקשה. miksha.
Okay it's just that everything is one. We'll say then repeated not
זהב zahav and not the what do you call it?
You'd have to do something with the יהיו. yihyu. Okay, which is
saying that one aspect of it is מעכב. me'akev. So it's a
little complicated but the upshot of this is like this: we know
from the יהיו yihyu one thing is מעכב. me'akev. We know from
the תעשו ta'asu it's not. The גמרא Gemara really, the real answer
besides just the economy of the word is that the גמרא Gemara
has a tradition as we're going to see already from the חשמונאים
Chashmonaim that gold is מעכב me'akev and there's a lot more latitude
when you're not using gold. But the גמרא Gemara? explains that in
the context of the economy of words. מקשה mikshah זהב zahav are
linked, so it's one thing to say that if it's gold it
has to be מקשה, mikshah, not gold it doesn't have to be
מקשה, mikshah, which we just said, but that allows for non-gold. You
can't say the opposite: you always need gold, but you don't always
need מקשה, mikshah, because then it doesn't explain how those
הויות havayot are gone and we wouldn't have any of this? We
couldn't tell today?
I don't know, I can't worry too much about that. Let's keep
on going. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this: okay,
מקשה דסיפא ולמעוטי דמאי
אתא? mikshah d'seifa u'l'mautei d'mai ata? How about the fact that it
says מקשה mikshah again at the end of the פסוק, pasuk מקשה
תעשה? mikshah ta'aseh? What's that needed for? So למעוטי חצוצרות, l'mautei chatzotzrot,
to exclude the case of the trumpets that משה Moshe made, because
we're going to find out that the trumpets that משה Moshe made
to gather the congregation are the exact opposite. Those have to be
silver, but they don't have to be one beaten unit, the exact
reverse. דתניא, d'tanya, learned in a ברייתא: braita: חצוצרות היו באות מן
העשת, chatzotzrot hayu ba'ot min ha-ashet, they would come from one beaten
unit, or ומן הכסף, u'min ha-kesef, and from silver. עשאן מן הגרוטאות
כשירה, asan min ha-gruta'ot ksheira, if you made it
from melting together different pieces it's valid.
משאר מיני מתכות פסולים, mishar minei matachot psulim, invalid, the exact opposite
of the מנורה. Menorah. So the גמרא Gemara says: ומאי פסקא דמשאר
מיני מתכות פסולים? u'mai paska d'mishar minei matachot psulim? Why is other
metals invalid?
דכתיב כסף והויה, d'chtiv kesef v'havaya, it says silver and shall be,
because it says מקשה חצוצרות כסף מקשה תעשה אותם והיו לך, mikshah
chatzotzrot kesef mikshah ta'aseh otam v'hayu lach, shall be for you, so
it means shall be exactly this way. So the גמרא Gemara says:
מן הגרוטאות נמי, min ha-gruta'ot nami, when it comes to pieces as
well, מקשה והויה, mikshah v'havaya, it says one beaten unit and shall
be. אמר רחמנא גבי מנורה מקשה היא, amar rachmana gabei Menorah mikshah
hi, by the מנורה Menorah it says it is a מקשה, mikshah,
it is one beaten unit, meaning the מנורה Menorah is the only
thing that we absolutely insist be one beaten unit. היא ולא חצוצרות,
hi v'lo chatzotzrot, the מנורה Menorah has to be beaten unit, the
חצוצרות chatzotzrot you have more latitude. So once by the חצוצרות chatzotzrot
you have latitude with the fact that it doesn't have to be
one beaten unit, if the פסוק pasuk is being more inclusive, it's
more inclusive in terms of that it doesn't have to be that
it's fuzzy. Once the תורה Torah is saying the opposite, once the
תורה Torah is saying that only the מנורה Menorah has to be
one beaten unit, the חצוצרות chatzotzrot do not, so what is the
תורה Torah insisting on on the חצוצרות? chatzotzrot? Not the beaten unit,
but the fact that it's silver. So the חצוצרות chatzotzrot are the
exact inverse of the מנורה, Menorah, must be silver, do not need
to be one beaten unit.
I'm sorry, where's the פסוק pasuk from מקשה היא mikshah hi from?
Which גמרא? Gemara By the חצוצרות? chatzotzrot? No, by מנורה, Menorah, right?
No, the מנורה, Menorah, וכפתוריה
ופרחיה ממנה יהיו, v'kaftoreiha u'fracheiha mimena yihyu, just the יהיו yihyu of
כפתור kaftor ופרח, u'ferach, but we apply that יהיו yihyu to everything.
Okay, now the גמרא says: תנו רבנן. tanu rabbanan. So we're going
to have a little brief interlude about the חצוצרות chatzotzrot and then
get back to the מנורה. Menorah. כל הכלים שעשה משה כשירים לו
וכשירים לדורות. kol ha-keilim she'asa Moshe ksheirim lo u'ksheirim l'dorot.
All of the vessels that משה Moshe made
were good for him and were good for all future generations. חצוצרות
שעשה משה כשרות לו ופסולות לדורות, chatzotzrot she'asa Moshe ksheirot lo u'psulot
l'dorot,
were used for his generation and not in the future. Of course,
in the future you weren't really having a moving camp either.
Right now it's just to be used for his generation, but we're
going to talk about him personally in a minute. Now, the primary
principle of the חצוצרות chatzotzrot was to move the camp, which obviously
wasn't needed once they entered ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, but it also
says that you should blow it on your קרבנות, korbanot, ועל זבחי
שלמיכם והיו לכם לזכרון v'al zivchei shalmeichem v'hayu lachem l'zikaron etc.
So that was only for משה Moshe or for משה's Moshe generation,
not for future generations. How do you know this? חצוצרות מאי טעמא,
chatzotzrot mai ta'ama, what's the reason?
אילימא דאמר קרא, eileima d'amar kra, if because the פסוק pasuk says:
עשה לך, aseh lach, make for you two חצוצרות, chatzotzrot, לך ולא
לדורות, lach v'lo l'dorot, which we'll interpret to mean your generation, not
future generations. אלא מעתה, ela me'ata, how about the other כלים keilim
of the משכן? mishkan? ועשית לך ארון עץ, v'asita lach aron etz,
make for yourself an ארון. Aron. Same thing? הכא נמי דלך ולא
לדורות? hacha nami d'lach v'lo l'dorot?
The ארון Aron, was only good for משה's Moshe generation, not for
future generations? They couldn't use the ארון? Of course not. אלא, ela,
so what does לך lach mean by the ארון? Why does the
תורה Torah say make for yourself an ארון? אלא למאן דאמר לך
משלך, ela l'man d'amar lach mishelcha,
either it means that משה Moshe is the one that is the
primary contributor or the contributor to the ארון, משה Moshe actually donated
the materials for the ארון. That's interesting. Or there's an opinion,
these are the opinions in the גמרא ביומא Gemara b'Yoma דף ע"ב:
daf ayin bet: כי ביחיד בשלחני רצה יותר
משלהם. ki b'yachid b'shulchani ratza yoter mishelahem. What God is saying is,
look, in the end money's given and to the משכן mishkan have
to be donated to the ציבור, tzibbur, have to be communal. Individuals
give, but they give it over to the community. So one way
of reading it is that משה Moshe was the contributor for the
ארון. That's what לך lach means. The other way of reading it
is God saying, look, if it were possible to not make this
a communal thing, I would be happy to have this is just
your ארון. משה, Moshe, you know, because the whole identity of משה
Moshe was the תורה Torah and it's תורת משה Toras Moshe and
so forth, but נעבעך, nebach,
right, the idea is that this is a communal,
this is a communal thing, so we're going to have to, we're
going to have to, you know, donate your funds to the entire
ציבור. tzibur. But on conceptual level, I would be happy for it
to be just your ארון. Okay, we can... there are obviously various,
you know, aggadic implications of all of that. But anyway, it doesn't
literally mean it's limited to משה's Moshe generation. So that's what it
means by the ארון, say the same by the חצוצרות. chatzotzrot. So
the גמרא says, האי
נמי מיבעי ליה להכי, hi nami miba'ei lei lehachi, so say the
same by the חצוצרות chatzotzrot that it's for... one of these דרשות,
drashot, but that it's good for other generations. So the גמרא says
no, שאני התם דאמר קרא, shani hatam de'amar kra, there it's different
because the פסוק pasuk says לך לך תרי זימני. lecha lecha trei
zimnei. It says לך lecha twice.
It says עשה לך, aseih lecha, make for yourself,
and והיו לך, ve-hayu lacha,
they shall be for you. So since it says you twice, we
understand that to mean it was only for משה's Moshe generation, not
to the future, which makes sense since their primary function was to
move the camp. Although they also served a function with the sacrifices,
their primary function was to move the camp, so that makes sense.
Okay, so now we're done with our little digression into חצוצרות. chatzotzrot.
שתהא מנורה she-te-ha-menorah does not have to be gold and when it's
not gold you have a lot more latitude of what to do,
but it absolutely has to... but if it is gold, then it
has to be from one beaten piece. Not gold actually it doesn't,
but if it is gold it has to be one beaten piece.
Now we're going to talk about, continue the discussion about the range
of different materials that the מנורה menorah can be made from. Let's
take a look.
תני רב פפא בריה דרבי חנין קמיה דרב יוסף. Tani Rav Pappa
brei de-Rabbi Chanin kamei de-Rav Yosef. So רב פפא Rav Pappa the
son of רבי חנין Rabbi Chanin taught in front of רב יוסף.
Rav Yosef. מנורה הייתה באה מן העשת—it Menorah hayetah ba'ah min ha-ashek
came from one beaten lump—ומן הזהב, u-min ha-zahav, from gold. עשה של
כסף כשרה, Asah shel kessef kesherah, if you made it of
silver it's kosher. של בעץ ושל אבר, Shel ba'atz ve-shel avar, min
דבעץ de-ba'atz which I didn't get a chance to look up, I
assume it's something like pewter. How do they translate בעץ? ba'atz? בדיל?
bedi'il? Oh, that's also... בדיל ועופרת. bedi'il u-oferet. אבר Avar is lead.
Atchin? What? Natin. Natin?
How do they translate it, Michael? Stannum, so that's tin. Tin. It
is tin. Oh, okay, look at that. Tin? Okay. Okay, so if
you made it of tin, so, or of silver, or of lead,
ושל גסטרון, ve-shel gisteron, or of גסטרון, gisteron, what's גסטרון? gisteron? A
metallic alloy. Thank you, or some other metal, so there רבי פוסל,
Rabbi posel, רבי invalidates. רבי יוסי בר יהודה מכשיר. Rabbi Yosef bar
Yehuda machshir. רבי יוסי בר יהודה Rabbi Yosef bar Yehuda says it's
kosher. Which means here it's silver, it's metals, but cheap metals. So
we say it can be other metals, can it even be cheap
metals? So that's that debate. של עץ ושל עצם ושל זכוכית, Shel
eitz ve-shel etzem ve-shel zechuchit, if it's wood or bone or glass,
meaning a non-metal, דברי הכל פסולה, divrei ha-kol psulah, everybody says it's
invalid. So that was רב פפא's Rav Pappa ברייתא baraita that he
said to רב יוסף. Rav Yosef. The debate is cheap metals, but
non-metals everybody says is invalid. אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said back
to him, said רב יוסף Rav Yosef back to רב פפא, Rav
Pappa, מאי דעתך? mai daitach? What's your logic about how you understand,
what are they debating? What do you think they're debating about? אמר
ליה, Amar lei, so he said back, בין מר בין מר כלל
ופרט וכלל דריש. bein mar bein mar klal u-prat u-klal darish. Everybody
says you read the פסוק כלל ופרט וכלל. klal u-prat u-klal. Because
the פסוק is ועשית מנורת, ve-asita menorat, which means כלל, klal, anything.
זהב, Zahav, gold, is a פרט. prat. מקשה תיעשה המנורה, Mikshah te'aseh
ha-menorah, make it, means of anything. כלל ופרט וכלל, Klal u-prat u-klal,
so the general principle of כלל ופרט וכלל klal u-prat u-klal is
it have to be, we broaden the specific to include anything like
it. Now the problem always with כלל ופרט וכלל klal u-prat u-klal
or ריבוי ומיעוט, ribu'i u-mi'ut, the problem is like it in
whose eyes? Who defines how like? That's the debate. Everybody says it
have to be like gold, but what does like mean? Does like
mean any metal, or does it mean any precious metal? That's how
I understand the debate. Okay, everybody agrees כלל ופרט וכלל. klal u-prat
u-klal. מר סבר מה פרט מפורש של מתכת אף כל של מתכת,
Mar savar ma prat meforash shel matechet, af kol shel matechet, one
says does it mean any metal. ומר סבר מה פרט מפורש דבר
חשוב אף כל דבר חשוב. U-mar savar ma prat meforash davar chashuv,
af kol davar chashuv. And so it has to be a precious
metal. So I understand they're debating, everybody says it has to be
like זהב, zahav, and they're debating whether that means metals or precious
metals.
Or other precious materials then are...
could be, but it doesn't sound like that. Yeah, we never say
that, it doesn't sound like that. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so רב
יוסף Rav Yosef said back to
רב פפא, Rav Pappa, סמי דידך מקמי דידי. s'mi didach mi-kamei didi.
Cross out your ברייתא baraita in favor of my ברייתא. baraita. I
have a better version of this debate, which I think is more
correct. דתניא, De-tanya, here's my
ברייתא, baraita, כלי שרת שעשאן של עץ. klei sharet she-asahan shel eitz.
How about other vessels? The interesting thing is that we're going to
learn that the מנורה menorah is a paradigm for other כלי שרת.
klei sharet. Now that's surprising, because the מנורה menorah constantly says זהב
זהב זהב. zahav zahav zahav. You would think it's more specific. But
once we say the מנורה menorah can be of other metals, that's
going to be a paradigm for כלי שרת. klei sharet. And anything
you can make the מנורה menorah out of, you can make, or
any כלי שרת klei sharet is valid of the materials that a
מנורה menorah could be made out of. It serves as the paradigm.
So here is the debate about כלי שרת. klei sharet. כלי שרת
שעשאן של עץ, Klei sharet she-asahan shel eitz, let's say you made
wooden כלי שרת. klei sharet. רבי פוסל, Rabbi posel, רבי says it's
invalid. רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה מכשיר, Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda machshir, and
Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda says it's כשר. kasher. So here they're not
debating cheap metals, they're debating non-metals, wood versus a metal, okay, so
therefore that's what I'd say they're debating. במאי קמיפלגי? Be-mai kamiflagi? What
are they debating? רבי דרש כלל ופרט וכלל. Rebbi darash klal u-prat
u-klal. Rebbi says כלל, פרט, וכלל. klal, prat, u-klal. So Rebbi would
say anything like gold, anything like gold means any metal, not precious
metal, any metal. That's would be his position. רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה,
Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda, הא רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה ha Rabbi Yose
b'Rabbi Yehuda that says even wood, so he's not כלל ופרט וכלל,
klal prat u-klal, he's ריבוי ומיעוט. ribuy u-mi'ut. דרש ריבוי ומיעוט. Darash
ribuy u-mi'ut. Now if you remember ריבוי ומיעוט ribuy u-mi'ut worked a
little different, כלל ופרט וכלל klal prat u-klal means anything like the
specific, anything like gold. So that could be all metals, all precious
metal. More than metal is not going to be like gold. So
that's Rebbi. It has to be metal. ריבוי מיעוט וריבוי Ribuy mi'ut
u-ribuy means if the Torah says a general statement, we basically assume
everything is included. Then if it says a specific word like gold,
we're only going to exclude things that are the most different from
gold. So it's going to be a much broader category. So
gold, silver, things that are
very low-grade materials like pottery, okay, something that is not at all
like a nice type of a material, but things like wood, that's
you know, it doesn't have to be like gold. It just it's
enough that it's not at the complete opposite end of the spectrum.
That's the point of ריבוי ומיעוט. ribuy u-mi'ut. Okay, so so he
says ריבוי ומיעוט. ribuy u-mi'ut. רבי דרש כלל ופרט. Rebbi darash klal
u-prat. So Rebbi says כלל ופרט. klal u-prat. ועשית מנורה Ve-asita menorah
כלל. klal. זהב טהור zahav tahor פרט. prat. וכיכר את המנורה Ve-kikar
et hamenorah חזר וכלל. hazar ve-klal. So that's your כלל ופרט וכלל.
klal prat u-klal. כלל ופרט וכלל אי אתה דן אלא כעין הפרט.
klal u-prat u-klal i ata dan ela ke-ein haprat. It has to
be like the specific, like gold. מה הפרט מפורש של
מתכת, mah haprat meforash shel mat'kaht, zeh she-omrei gold is metal, אף
כל של מתכת. af kol shel mat'kaht. Anything that's metal. רבי יוסי
ברבי יהודה דרש ריבוי ומיעוט. Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda darash ribuy u-mi'ut.
Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda says the ריבוי ומיעוט ribuy u-mi'ut which is
more inclusive. ועשית מנורה Ve-asita menorah ריבה. riba. So instead of using
the word כלל, klal, we use word ריבה, riba, but it means
sort of including everything. זהב טהור zahav tahor מיעט. mi'et. That's excluding
a few things. וכיכר את המנורה Ve-kikar et hamenorah חזר וריבה hazar
ve-riba and then it tells another including. ריבוי מיעוט וריבוי, Ribuy mi'ut
u-ribuy, ריבה הכל. riba hakol. That includes everything. ומה ריבית? U-mah ribisah?
So what did it include? ריבה כל מילי. Ribah kol mili. So
everything starts off being included. ומה מיעט? U-mah mi'et? So when we
have to exclude, we're only going to exclude one thing that is
most different. מיעט של חרס. Mi'et shel cheres. It excludes pottery. So
you say they're debating precious metals versus all metals, and everybody says
it has to be like gold, I'm saying they're debating whether it
has to be at all like gold or just not opposite of
gold. And therefore Rebbi says all metal, and Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda
says no, the only thing that's excluded is pottery. So he's going
to say, so therefore, therefore he says, except my ברייתא, braita, mine
is better than yours. So he says,
אדרבה סמי דידך מקמי דידי adereba samei de-didach mik-me-didi? Maybe my ברייתא
braita is better than yours? Why should I reject my ברייתא? braita?
Maybe I have the more accurate version of the debate that's debating
whether it's all metals or just precious metals? So the גמרא is
going to say no and we'll pick up with it. I just
see one sentence, we're going to have a whole string of ברייתות
braitot that show that the debate is about non-metals, not about precious
metals. לא תעלה דעתך, lo ta'aleh da'atach, that doesn't make sense. דתניא,
Detanya, we learned in a ברייתא, braita, אין לו זהב מביא אף
של כסף של נחושת של ברזל של בדיל של עופרת, ein lo
zahav mevi af shel kesef shel nechoshet shel barzel shel bedil shel
oferet, sounds like the כלי מדין klei Midian what they got from
Midian. If you don't have gold you can bring of any other
metal the מנורה. menorah. רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה מכשיר אף בשל עץ.
Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda machshir af be-shel etz. Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda
says even wood. So there are many ברייתות braitot that show they're
not debating metals versus precious metals, they're debating metals versus non-metals. And
we will finish up with that tomorrow and then we will finally
get to our night בלאט blatt even in a minute, because we
didn't get finished.